[Music]
Heat.
All right. Okay. Here we are. Here we
go. Welcome everybody to Ask Abijit
episode 278.
I hope everybody is doing fantastic. Let
us see who all is there on the live chat
with us on this live stream. I can see
Dhi Raj Rahul Pajwell Gupta Nishad
Atalia Boston bread anonymous scientist
Bonjour Avin hello Vikash PJ Aush Singh
Jay Gum Samripati Miscellaneous Di Raj
Raal Ain
Geopolitical Dub from Indor good evening
sir Sagar to Jes krishna Adita Viml
hello Boston bread again Nishadali
yuvraat singhawat Shri Ramchandra Radhir
Aisha Mishra hello ma'am
Dhi Raj Praul Gupta Gravity
HB Namaskar Miscellaneous Nabaradas
Shivas Sai Yuvra Singh Shikawan Sag to
Yaneshwar Raju
uh Adita Ashish Raj Sid Kayushman Matur
Di Raj Avin Umar Maheshwari good evening
Durya hello Adita Viml hello happy
Janmash to me to everybody really now
patriotic Yrad Singh Shik Kawad Shivani
Maheshwari Akil Patak Negro Arian Patel
from Philly Dy Raj Polar Bear who else
do we have Krishna Ragunat from the
Suryam Netherlands MK Mr. Sena, Saita,
Sham, Gulkarni, Stark, Tanmay, Akil,
Patak, Aayushan, Patriotic, Vicash, PJ,
Nimish, Gupta, Sedhart, MK, Rohan, Suna,
uh, yes Donald Trump and Plutin,
Chetan, Ajab, Stark, Savia, Hub, Happy
Mash, Ashugam,
uh, Tanmay, Aninda, Bachari, Sagar,
Torat, ML from Hawaii, Bas the johni
uh nares
says good evening and rip to your hip
flexors sitting 8 hours a day you have
no idea what I'm capable of
rohan suna
kash keedar tanay sedhart agniva raana
summer afternoon animesh pauli raj sigma
realm and so many other people all right
good to see you all thank you so much
for being on the live chat I'm going to
take History questions today. Napoleon
Singh Shikhawatul. Hello. So I'll take
history questions today. A bunch of
history questions. History questions are
always super diverse. Lots of questions.
I am only able to take a few. I've
selected 25 or 26 questions. That's
about it. And we'll take as many as
possible. Uh before we go into that, I
will take one geopolitics question
because it's super relevant, super
important. Lots of people have asked
about Putin and Trump. They're meeting.
What's the outcome? What does it mean?
So you see geopolitics,
today's geopolitics is tomorrow's
history and yesterday's geopolitics is
today's history. So it's all
interconnected. So let's take one
question, one one geopolitical topic and
I'll not put questions on the screen
because plenty of people have asked
that. Uh before that somebody's Adita is
saying how do you sit 8 hours a day in
one go? Any suggestions? You've got to
take care of your fitness and your
health and then only you can uh have the
stamina to sit for eight hours a day and
it's something you develop over time.
It's not something you can just start
doing from day one. It takes time. It
takes a lifetime of experience and
practice to do that to be able to pull
that off. And you need to be reasonably
fit as a human being and flexible and
all that to be able to do that.
Otherwise, it's going to mess up your
entire posterior chain, anterior chain,
everything. So, you've got to take care,
you've got to take the precautions. Only
then you can pull it off, right? So take
care of your fitness, stamina, health,
food, flexibility, all of that. And
build up the stamina for sitting and
working at a stretch. Start with 1 hour
and then you can increase it. All right.
Now, Napole, what am I saying? Napoleon,
no. Putin and Trump, what what's the
deal? The the two gentlemen, the two
leaders met yesterday in Alaska. What's
the outcome of that? Did it achieve
something this meeting? Right. So let's
focus on the substance. Let's forget
about the optics. We saw a lot of
optics, right? I mean what's the optics
that we witnessed? Oh, all the
symbolism, the location which is Alaska,
then Putin coming in, Trump doing that
fancy handshake of his in which he pulls
the guy's hand towards himself and then
pats his back of the hand that way. That
symbolism, the red carpet drawn out for
Mr. Putin. The two leaders sitting in
Trump's limuine, the fighter jets jets
flanking the limusine's path, the B2
bomber flanked by fighter jets that flew
over Mr. Putin when he met with Mr.
Trump. All of that, that's symbolism,
right? That's a show of force by the US.
The US president, Mr. Trump decided to
do a show of force. It's an attempt to
What's a show of force? A show of force
is an attempt to either impress or
intimidate somebody.
When do you do a show of force? When do
you feel the need to show some force?
You feel that need when you're actually
in a position of weakness.
Right? So a show of force is an attempt
to compensate for some weakness to hide
your weakness.
Do you think Mr. Putin was impressed by
the show of force? Do you think so?
Yeah. Mr. Putin has met with every
single US president in the in more than
the past quarter century. He's met them
dozens of times. He knows what US
presidents are like. He's not going to
be impressed with the show of force. He
himself has plenty of force. He has more
than 5,000 nuclear warheads and god
knows what else. It's not going to
impress him. Right? If in case Mr. Trump
were to visit Moscow to meet with Mr.
Putin. Do you think Putin will show off
his weaponry and all that? He won't do
that. When you are powerful, you don't
need you don't feel the need to
demonstrate force. You keep it implicit.
That's what makes it stronger and more
powerful.
So that's the symbolism. Let's let's
forget about the symbolism. Let's focus
on the substance. The two leaders met.
They had substantial talks with their
utrage 2 and a half hours plus. That's
what one hears, right? And then there
was after that uh an address by both
leaders first by Mr. Putin and then by
Mr. Trump.
And if you see the body language and all
of that that is not simple isn't that is
more substance. It indicates what
happened the dynamics between the two
sty between the two sides and the two
leaders. Mr. Putin looked super
comfortable. He looked good. Mr. Trump
looked a little nervous. Just the body
language. See the thing is in this
negotiation that happened
both sides wanted something that's why
this happened right what was what is it
that Mr. Trump wanted what's the minimum
that Mr. Trump wanted I think he said
what he wanted he said that he will be
very disappointed if there is no deal at
all or or no ceasefire that's what he
said what happened so the minimum
expectation from Mr. Trump's side was at
least some form of ceasefire maybe a
temporary ceasefire so that negotiation
negotiations can go forward was there a
ceasefire agreed upon absolutely nothing
even the minimum expectation that Mr.
Trump had did not materialize.
You see, because both sides were were
negotiating from different positions.
One from a position of strength, one
from a position of weakness. Who was in
a position of weakness? Who was in a
position of strength? The side with the
territorial advantage and the upper hand
in the Ukraine war is in a position of
strength. That's that is Mr. Putin. Mr.
Trump is under pressure. He has
unleashed a war of tariffs on the world.
It's biting him back because it's biting
the US public. They are having to pay
the tariffs. It's not the other nations
that are paying the tariffs. It's the US
population, the public that's paying the
tariffs. It's going to make him
increasingly unpopular. Secondly, he has
made promises that he has not been able
to keep. Mr. Trump, he said on day one
of my presidency, I will end the Ukraine
war. Well, what happened? So, he's
desperate to have at least a ceasefire.
So, Trump was bargaining, negotiating
from a position of weakness. Putin was
negotiating from position of strength
and then clearly there was no agreement
there was no deal and Mr. Trump had said
before this summit happened that he'll
be very disappointed if there is no deal
if there's no ceasefire while he did not
get any deal any ceasefire and in the
address that both leaders gave to the
media
both leaders spoke first Mr. Putin then
Mr. Trump and Mr. Putin made his red
lines abundantly clear. He said that
Europe and the West must respect
Russia's red lines and he made those red
lines abundantly clear. The red lines
are Russia's national interests and
Europe's security position has to take
into account Russia's national interests
and Russia's security position. Right?
And he said and so on. So he made his
position abundantly clear. I don't know
what Trump Mr. Mr. Trump really said his
uh address did not really have much
substance and then put Mr. Putin said
that you know the next meeting will be
in Moscow and Mr. Trump said yeah maybe
that can happen that sort of thing.
So maybe this is just the first meeting
in a long series of meetings. Uh Mr.
Zalinsky obviously wasn't invited
because we know how it goes when Mr.
Zillinski is there and uh yeah Mr.
Zalinsky and and the EU are essentially
the the roadblock the obstacle in in the
in the way of any kind of ne ceasefire.
Well all Mr. Trump has to do if he wants
a ceasefire is to stop funding the war.
That's it. So anyhow, nothing has
emerged out of this summit. Nothing has
happened. Mr. Putin, I think he came
back stronger. He came back as the
winner. He came back as somebody who
rebuffed Mr. Trump's uh,
you know, desire to
reach some kind of deal to get a
ceasefire out of Mr. Putin. Did not
happen. He did not get m give Mr. Trump
what he wanted. And Mr. Putin I'm sure
must have made demands that Trump
obviously can't fulfill or maybe he
wants to fulfill them but he is facing
various kinds of problems
obstacles. Mr. Trump wants to gain
access to the minerals of Ukraine and
all that. So both leaders have some
thing to gain but uh Mr. Putin is
perfectly willing to play the long game
as we know very well.
You understand? He's been playing the
long game ever since the war started.
slow war strategy, long war strategy,
frozen conflict strategy. The longer it
drags, the longer it goes on, the more
the West has to pay the price. And the
longer there's no ceasefire, the more
the more pressure Mr. Trump will face.
Mr. Putin, it suits him very well. Is he
he is perfectly happy to be patient. So
that's where we are. Trump is in a
hurry. Putin is in is is is in no hurry
at all. So it's advantage Putin right
now and Russia's war economy like they
say it's doing really well. So uh that's
where we are. No outcome. Advantage
Russia advantage Mr. Putin. Mr. Lavrov
came wearing a CCCP shirt t-shirt. Very
very cheeky of him. So that's where we
are. All right. That's my update about
the Ukraine conflict and the Trump Putin
um summit. There was mention of tariffs
and all and Mr. Trump has said that okay
since we are negotiating I will not
impose further tariffs on nations that
are purchasing Russian oil. I think the
tariffs that Trump has imposed on India
are an attempt to pressurize Mr. Putin
pressurize Russia
because if he puts India in a position
where India may have to rethink its
purchase of purchases of Russian oil
that puts the Russian economy under
stress so it's all interconnected.
Anyhow that's how it's gone. Now let's
take some questions that I have selected
from the comments.
Where do we begin?
Um, Hersa says, "Believe it or not, our
channel your problems of India which are
the near of the hour which have been
echoing over the years have somehow
reached the top level. We can hear from
Prime Minister himself. Um, only to look
forward our actions as you say, God
speed Jindustan." Yeah, Mr. Mr. Mr. Modi
during his 15th of August speech, he did
mention many of the topics that I've
been speaking about for I've been really
speaking about for the past few years,
haven't it? Haven't I? Uh illegal
immigration, that's one issue that I
have been speaking about. I I've been
speaking about the need to become
technologically more sovereign, the need
to develop our own jet engines, all of
that. Uh technological sovereignty,
military um sovereignty, all of that. So
many of the topics that I've been
speaking about, I think Mr. Modi spoke
about them especially illegal
immigration the demographic initiative
that is starting all of that so it's
good to see that I I would not give
myself the credit that because of me Mr.
Modi Zupar no obviously he's the leader
of the country he knows these better
than me or better than anybody else and
I'm glad that this is being addressed
now so I'm I'm really glad to see that
but we have to see how this translates
into actions and we will wait and watch
for that now Malik says I am 19 I was 15
when I first saw you in a podcast in
which you had indeed said that this
decade is a decade of changes in which
changes will happen on a weekly basis I
was naive
to understand that back then what you
told us but now I fully understand and
I'm and I'm aware of what you had said
came to be true so can you expand on
this well thank you first of all Malik
said I really appreciate your kind words
and the fact that you've been watching
me for so long so I have been saying
this I mean the first geopolitical
podcast I did was probably in the year
2021 when in India nobody used the term
geopolitics at that time everybody was
was a strategic affairs expert And the
topic was called strategic affairs and I
went on the beer biceps podcast with
reanir and I discussed geopolitics and
somehow that term caught on now
everybody's a geopolitics expert that's
fine that's good so it's I think in that
first podcast that I had said that there
are times when nothing happens for for a
century no change happens for a century
and then there are periods of history
where decades of change happen in just
weeks or months or years decades worth
of changes and I had said that the 2020s
is going to be that that sort of decade
where decades worth of change the change
that you typically see over decades will
happen in weeks or months and we are
seeing that right so how do I expand
upon this right you want me to expand
upon this so you can expand upon this by
well giving historical precedents
there have been multiple periods in
history where tremendously
vast broad and deep changes have
happened in in short periods of time
Right. One ex I mean let's look at the
past 1,000 years only. For example, h
the year 1066
1066 the Norman conquest of England
happened overnight all of a sudden
happened out of nowhere. The English
king Harold Goodwinson he was in the
north of England fighting off fighting
off his brother who had allied with a
Danish king called Harald Hardrad.
And after a tremendous battle, the
battle of Stamford Bridge in which the
English king won. It was an exhausting
battle. The English king won. He had to
kill his brother and his brother's ally,
King Harold Hadra of Denmark. And the
moment the battle is over, he hears word
that that that William of of Normandy
has has just landed on the southern
shore of England. So he has to go all
the way from north of England all the
way to to the south of England and fight
a battle. until the battle of Hastings
which he loses because of bad luck. He
got a arrow in the ear in the eye and
William the Conqueror who was the
William of Normandy who until then was
called William the Bastard because he
was illegitimate. He suddenly
transformed into William the Conqueror
and so much changed in a m matter of
weeks and months in England. The entire
old system disappeared.
the Anglo-Saxon, the Saxon
system of governance, the Saxon rule,
the Saxon nobility, everything
evaporated overnight and the Normans
took over and it was a tremendous change
in England and it had wide-ranging
repercussions for the whole of Europe
eventually. Right? So that's 1066.
Tremendous change in a matter of weeks
and months. 1258
Baghdad the fall of Baghdad
it fell to the Mongols uh it fell to
Hulu Khan I think great grandson of Shri
Chingghist Khan so at that time the
Islamic world was at its pinnacle
it was the pinnacle of the golden age of
Islam
and this the center of the Islamic world
was Baghdad and they had these libraries
and universities one library and
university and whatnot and in which they
had amassed a great amount of wisdom and
knowledge mostly from India science,
mathematics,
uh pharmarmacology, tox toxicology,
astronomy, mathematics,
so much more and and that had given rise
to this e fluoresence of culture of art
all of that in the Islamic world, right?
And Baghdad was the center of that.
Baghdad was the seat of the caliphate
and Hulle Guhan enter Hool Guhan the
Mongol the great grandson or grandson I
think grand whatever it is of Shiring
Isan and he besieges Baghdad in 1258 he
sacks Baghdad puts the city to the to
the to the sword and the torch destroys
everything and overnight the Islamic
world changed the golden age was over
like that and the Islamic world turned
inward words and it was it was it was a
seismic
event in the Islamic world. Nothing was
the same ever again. So that is another
massive massive change. Then you have uh
1453 the end of the Byzantine Empire,
the fall of Constantinople which
completely upended the the the
geopolitics of that time in Europe. It
suddenly turned the Turks into a massive
force and it all culminated with a siege
siege of Vienna when Sullean the
Magnificent
took the Christian world by the throat.
Of course they did not succeed in taking
Vienna but you know that sort of thing.
So
the Ottoman Empire destroyed the
Byzantine Empire, annihilated the
Byzantine Empire. the Bosphorus straight
this extremely vital set of choke points
the Bosphorus and the Dardinels. So that
flipped the control of that flipped
right and uh the trade routes completely
were reshaped. the Eurasian trade routes
the great power dynamics changed u and
that is what caused that that is what
precipitated European efforts to find a
different sea route to India because
earlier it used to go through the
through the Byzantine Empire and that's
where Vasco the Gama and before that
Columbus and all that's where they come
into the picture so that changed world
history completely right then you have
world war I that's another great example
for from the last century the world the
first world war essentially everything
changed in about two weeks two weeks
there's the assassination of the ark arc
duke France Ferdinand
and the Austria Austrohungarian Empire
issues an ultimatum to Serbia and the
ultimatum was designed in such a way
that the Serbians can't accept it
so then in a few days the
Austro-Hungarian Empire declares war as
a consequence Germany declares war on
Russia and France together and Germany
invades Belgium. And the moment Germany
invades Belgium, Britain has to enter
the war because Britain was the
guaranter of security of Belgium. In a
matter of like less than two weeks, all
the dominoes fall in the world is at I
mean the western world is at war and
obviously it had ripple effects across
the world including India, right?
Because Indian forces were the bulwark
of the British armed forces
and so many more examples. So there are
times in history I've just given a few
there are so many more there are so many
more the Bronze Age collapse and so much
more I mean you can go on forever so
there are times there are periods of
time in history where so much change
happens in a very compressed condensed
amount of time and that's what I mean
and this is one of those time periods we
haven't seen major wars yet the Ukraine
war is is is a problem yeah obviously uh
but you know the situation such that
major conflict could could emerge
anytime there multiple flash points in
the world. So that's what I was talking
about when I was talking about uh
decades of changes happening in in weeks
or months. That's exactly what I was
talking about. Hope that puts it into
context.
Now let's take another question. Amisha
says, "What's the difference between an
empire, a kingdom, and a dynasty?"
Right? So a dynasty is something that is
pertinent to empires as well as
kingdoms. So let's start with dynasties
first. A dynasty is typically one family
that rules for an extended period of
time. So the father, let's say, starts a
kingdom, becomes king, then his son
takes over, then his grandson takes
over, then great-grandson, and there's a
succession of kings all from the same
lineage. That's a dynasty, right?
In the US, you have the Bush dynasty.
George W. Bush, uh, George Bush senior,
the president in who won the presidency
in 1998.
Uh, sorry. 1988. I'm I'm sorry. I beg
your pardon. 1988. And then George W.
Bush who won in 2004, I believe. All the
way up to 2012, he was president. So
that's one. There's the Clinton dynasty.
And then George Bush the senior has
another son who tried to be president,
right? So that's a political dynasty.
That's a political dynasty. When it
comes to kingdoms and empires, well, the
Moria Empire was an empire. It was also
a dynasty because you have the the the
empire starts with Chandra Gupta Moria.
Then his son becomes king becomes
emperor after him Bindhusar. Then
Bindusar's son Ashoke the great becomes
king emperor. And there's a whole list
of kings all the way up to the last one
who was assassinated by Pushamutra
Pushit.
So succession of kings emperor sorry who
are all from the same family the same
lineage. That's a dynasty.
Another example is the Gupta Empire.
Same it starts with a king called
Gatodkach in Magad. He was a smalltime
king. But then his successors, his son,
grandson, they became greater and
greater and eventually you have someone
like uh Samudra Gupta who conquered the
whole of the subcontinent. Then you have
Kumar Gupta who was a great great great
king. you your tundra Gupta and so some
of these emperors they went all the way
to Bahalik which is beyond Afghanistan
and so much more you have the chas and
so on so it's entire it's family family
lineage lineages these are that's
dynasties okay
so typically
a kingdom typically has one dynasty
sometimes you have multiple dynasties of
course yeah
right right um so that's a dynasty it's
a lineage of rules ers all starting from
one ancestor and going down going down
from essentially from father to son or
or in the same family. Now what's a
kingdom? A kingdom is is is is
a state that's ruled by a king. A state
means a political entity with a defined
geographical boundary that is ruled by
one king. That's a kingdom. A kingdom
typically doesn't have vasals.
An empire is a massive kingdom.
And the king is called the emperor in an
empire. And in the the difference
between kingdoms and empires is that
empires are vast. They cover huge
geographical regions. And they typically
project power way beyond their
boundaries by making other kingdoms
their vasals.
The Moria Empire, the Gupta Empire,
these are examples. The Tola Empire. Um
so many examples. Yeah. The the the
Kushan Empire, the Roman Empire, the the
Egyptians. So many examples. These are
empires. The US has vasals all over the
place. That's an empire, right? South
Korea is a king, sorry, North Korea is a
kingdom. They don't have vasals. It's
just one unit, one family. That's a
dynasty. Kim Ilsung, Kim Jong, il Kim
Jong-un,
three in the same family, right? That's
dynasty and that's one kingdom. They
don't have any vasals. They are the
vasals of China, more or less. So, I
hope that explains the difference
between kingdom, empire, and and
dynasty.
Right.
Huku Bahadur Khadka says, "How did the
Nepalese identity forge? Was it based on
the conquests of Shri Pritwir and Sha or
is it something that's a myth?"
Look,
the Nepal's identity is not a myth. It
is definitely a real thing. Now, let's
examine the history of Nepal. First of
all, let's go to the map and just try
and understand the the geography before
we get into the history because I I
always I'll tell you that you know the
map explains a lot. So let's take a look
at the map and we're going to the
northern part of India Nepal uh beyond
the northern part of India Kmandu. So if
you look at the geography of Nepal I
mean it's not really visible here unless
we okay we'll even if I put the
satellite image you may get a better
idea perhaps. So you see the southern
part of Nepal is called the Tarai region
the plains
and uh it's a pretty large region and
about half of Nepal's population lives
in in the Tarai region and the people
who live in the Tarai region of Nepal
are essentially more or less identical
as the people of Uttar Pradesh and Bihar
same people then you have the Bahad
region the hills of Nepal which is the
major part of Nepal and that's where the
mainly the the Bahadi people, the Gorha
people live. Kathmandu is the center
obviously the capital and that's where
the political power lies in Nepal in the
Bahad region and then you have the
northern regions which is the Himalayan
regions where you have other people who
live and that borders Chinese occupied
Tibet. So that is the geography of Nepal
and the center of power has always lies
has always resided in the uh Kathmandu
region for quite a long time. So that is
just briefly the the the
geography of Nepal. Now if you look at
the history
yes Britaran Sha was you can consider
him to be the founder of the kingdom of
Nepal. If you look at the history of
Nepal going back 2 and a half thousand
years let's say okay let's not go back
too far only 2 and a half thousand
years. So Nepal was part of at least a
couple of Mahajanapadas of the ancient
period the present day region of Nepal.
You had the Viji Mahajanapad. Okay. It
was located north of the Ganga and it
extended all the way into the Pahar
region, the present day Pahari region of
of Nepal and the capital was Vishali,
right? So and and the Viji confederacy
it it included dynasties like the lichi
dynasty and they have historically been
connected with Nepal and you know I
think at least one branch of the lichi
dynasty ruled Nepal until the start of I
don't know this this second second
millennium AD right uh so that's the
lichi dynasty and and uh I think it was
Chundra Gupta of the Gupta dynasty who
married a Lichi princess And that
elevated his status and you know he I
mean it really made a difference for
him. So that's how highly regarded the
lichi dynasty was. So Nepal much of
Nepal was at one point in time part of
the Viji or Vajji Mahajanapad. Then some
parts of Nepal were also part of the
Kosala Mahajanapadas territory. Okay.
Parts of southern Nepal the Taray
region. Uh so the Lichi dynasty was very
prominent in Nepal and they ruled all
the way up to the at least the 9th or
10th centuries AD possibly in the second
millennium AD also and Nepal was
obviously part part of the Morian
Empire. Okay. As as Magad rose and
extended its power everywhere. Well much
of Nepal came became incorporated into
the into the Mad sorry the the Mori
Empire. I'm sure it was part of the
Kushan Empire as also and also part of
the Gupta Empire. I'm pretty sure about
that.
So there you have it. Now when it comes
to Priti Daran Sha, um he conquered the
Navar Valley also called the Nepal
Valley in 1768.
So he was a king of the Gora dynasty
and he was not the founder. The founder
I forget the name of the founder. You
can look it up. The founding of the
dynasty happened a couple of centuries
before Pritwin Naran Sha's conquest of
the nawir valley and pritu narancha was
the greatest king of this dynasty and he
expanded his kingdom and that's what
became Nepal and Nepal the British Raj
never incorporated it into the British
Raj because they wanted it to remain a
buffer state between British occupied
India and Tibet where there was some
hints of Chinese uh uh involvement. So
they they wanted a buffer. They wanted
to keep the Chinese away because the
Chinese were trying to interfere in
Tibet.
uh so Nepal as a separate entity as a
distinct entity emerges around 1768
with the establishment of this kingdom
or an expansion of the kingdom by Shri
Prasid Narancha and ever since that time
it's been a distinct entity distinct uh
political entity a distinct state and it
has remained that so that is essentially
the the birth of the Nepalese identity
as a separate identity That's around the
time of Shri Priti Narayan Sha. Hope
that explains the matter.
Okay. Survves WMA says, "Why did India's
empires from the Indis Valley and and
Moras the Guptas uh and and Moras the
Guptas and Cholas and Mughals collapse
without the civilizational freef fall
seen in Rome, the Maya lowlands or the
late Bronze Age world? Every elsewhere
cities, scripts and economies vanished
in India culture, trade and regional
power often thrived. Will today's global
empires fall like their ancient
counterparts leaving behind little? And
if they do, will India emerge again with
its core intact while others fade? Okay,
before I address the question, I would
not consider the Mughal Empire to be an
Indian empire civilizationally or
culturally. Yeah, of course, it was
based in India. It was based out of
Delhi for quite some time but it was
like the Chinese say the Chinese have a
term for this sort of empire a conquest
dynasty. It's a foreigners. It's a bunch
of foreigners who have come and occupied
the land, conquered the land and they
create an empire. So the Yuan dynasty is
a classic example of a conquest dynasty.
The Yuan dynasty its founder is
considered to be Shri Chingish Khan and
the first proper emperor out of China
was Shir Kublhan.
So that's the Yuan dynasty. It was
Mongols ruling over China out of
Beijing.
That's a conquest dynasty, not a Chinese
dynasty per se. Not not really Chinese
dynasty ethnically. Eventually they
culturally they became Chinese slowly.
So when it comes to the Mughal Empire,
it was not really an Indian dynasty. I
not see it as an Indian dynasty
culturally or civiliz civilizationally
at all. But anyhow, the bigger point is
what you're making over here. So we've
had empires and various uh kingdoms and
and states that have come and come and
gone risen and fallen in India. Another
example of a conquest dynasty is in
India is the Kushan dynasty the Kushan
Empire but they became thoroughly
Indianized and ethnically they were not
that different from India from Indians
anyhow. Uh so yeah we've had the rise
and fall of dynasties in India the and
and empires the morian empire which was
a pan India pan subcontinent empire
eventually uh declined and fell it f and
and the successor state was the push was
the shunga empire and you've had the
rise and fall of the kusan empire uh
which spread Indian culture far and wide
right uh far and wide then you had the
Gupta empire with the jola empire and so
many empires they came and fell they
came and went they came and went
But you did not see any civilizational
freef fall in India. The culture and the
civilization persisted and actually even
thrived kept on thriving. Right? That's
what happened. There are times when the
culture doesn't do very well.
Civilization is not doing that great
because there's the absence of a great
power that supports the culture. But
that's how it is. Now when it comes to
the Mayans,
uh the Maya lowlands etc. See the Mayan
culture it it begins in the first half
of the first millennium AD around 200
300 AD that's where you have the
emergence of the Maya Maya city states
and all that and then Maya culture
really thrives that's that's what
happened and it it saw a downfall around
700 to 900 AD or something like that
around that time you can look up the
exact dates okay I don't memorize dates
but it's around that time u and the Maya
Empire the Maya region is essent
essentially the Yucatan plus region of
Mexico. Let's quickly Google it since we
have a map. Let's take advantage of the
map. So, we're talking about this part
of Mexico. Okay, the Yucatan region and
and
larger than Yucatan but overall centered
around Yucatan. That's where you had the
Maya uh culture civilization and that
declined and then eventually you had the
triple alliance the Aztec Empire like
they like they call it which uh came in
its place in in the same region but the
Maya culture and civilization never
really vanished
never really vanished. Even today you
have people who speak Mayan derived
languages and and practice you what you
could call Mayan culture. So despite the
fall of the Mayan Empire essentially
Mayan culture or civilization did not
disappear
entirely today it's more or less kind of
ex semi-extinct it's because of the
European influence see heran Cortez the
the Spanish concistador
destroyed
destroyed the triple alliance empire the
Aztec empire I think he reached Mexico
in 1519 or something and he unleashed
horrific devastation on on the people
and the and the culture. So the Mayan
empire the culture it declined because
of that. You have Rome. Yeah, Rome was
destroyed by Christianity by the way.
True true fact. Um late Bronzage world
does still the we still you know there
there's still a lot of dispute about
what really happened. Was it climate
change? Was it some environmental
catastrophes, tsunamis, earthquakes?
What was it that destroyed the late
Bronze world in the Mediterranean
eastern Mediterranean region and what
they call the fertile crescent? the the
the Mesopotamian region and so on.
There's still big questions about it.
How did so many empires fall and
disappear entirely, vanish without a
trace? But in India,
empires have come and gone. But our
culture, our civilization has remained
intact. What happened? Why is it so?
Because see, today it's not the case
really. Today I'm speaking a foreign
language. I'm more comfortable in a
foreign language. I'm wearing foreign
clothes. I read books that are in a
foreign language. Our education system
is a foreign education system. Our our
our so-called constitution is entirely
foreign. Our our system of governance
governance is foreign. Our education
system is foreign. Everything is foreign
here today. That all the institutions
are foreign. Do you really see us as a
civilization today? We are falling.
We're falling. You see what's happened?
Something changed. We were conquered by
foreign foreign cultures
and they they took systematic steps to
to break us to break us culturally and
civilizationally and it's succeeding
after 1947. It is the Indian government
that has done that continued that and
taken it forward various successive
Indian governments right um so why did
that not happen before
before the past let's say 250 300 years
let's say 500 years why did not did it
not happen because whichever kingdoms
and empires came and went in India they
were all
offspring of the same civilization
so you
The Moria Empire that comes and rises
and reaches its pinnacle then eventually
declines and falls. It is replaced by
the Shunga Empire. Same culture, same
civilization. They did not launch any
attack or assault on our civilization.
They strengthened it in their own way.
Maybe a different way but but they
strengthened it. So the focus was no
longer on both the dharma. It was on
what we now call Hinduism, Hindu dharma.
Right? in the pushunga empire uh during
the Moria empire the focus at least
during ashok's time was more on both the
dharma and one of his descendants
focused on jay dharma of course yeah we
know that um then you have the gupta
empire that comes that the kushan empire
the koshan empire also propagated our
culture and civilization not just in
India all across the world as far as
possible at least especially eastwards
towards China it is Shri Karanka and his
and his descendants who started
propagating getting Indian culture
eastwards all the way to China. He's the
Kaneshko who started that started the
process. So he spread our culture far
and wide. He did more than anybody else
to spread our culture beyond our shores
beyond our natural boundaries. Then you
had the Gupta empire once again a
beautiful efflloresence of the same
culture and civilization in a different
shape and form. So and then you have the
cholers who who took our culture all the
way to the Phil all the way as far as
says the Philippines and so on and so
on. So it's always been the same
civilization that has given rise to
multiple empires. So the collapse of an
empire did not destroy our culture. It
was too deep rooted to destroy. Our
culture is 60 70,000 years old. Our
culture is is the continuation of of the
culture of the people who came with the
with the last out of Africa migration
about 70 or whatever thousand years ago.
The population that we have in India is
a descendant of that ancient population.
And we have always had cultural
continuity. We know the cultural
continuity goes back at least 10,000
years. It may go back 50, 60, 70,000
years possibly. We don't know. So
because our culture and civilization is
so deep rooted, it's always been
resilient. It's withtood all these, you
know, ups and downs. When it comes to
other cultures, well, they've been
destroyed. So Rome had its own
polytheistic culture which was part of
the same greater Indo-Uropean culture
and religion and it was destroyed by
Christianity. So Christianity sought to
destroy to uproot the native culture and
religion and replace it with
Christianity and that's what happened.
So that's why civilization
was destroyed in Rome. Same in Greece,
same everywhere in Europe. when it comes
to the Americas, genocide, cultural and
demic genocide.
So, and and the same was attempted in
the past 10,000 years in India. And now
we are seeing it coming, you know,
bearing fruit because now we are we are
increasingly dassinated.
Our our youth don't even know what their
culture is. They they don't see any
connection with their culture. It's it's
becoming more and more apparent today.
So now it is succeeding in India. Maybe
in a 100 years the same thing will have
happened in India. Maybe we will our our
descendants will be practicing a whole
different set of religions. It's very
possible if we don't if we not careful
about this.
Okay. Amisha says which what war in
world history is considered to be the
most brutal in the bloodiest war? Well,
the answer actually the straightforward
if you want the number one war obviously
it's the second world war. The the worst
war of all. Okay. Uh it is believed that
it it killed between 80 to 85 million
people. the second world war. So that's
easy. But there have been lots of other
wars that have been frightening but
people don't know about them. So let's
let's Google Google a few of these shall
we? We will start with China. China is
China really features a lot in this. So
for example uh how many of you have
heard of the
prek kingdoms
civil war three kingdom civil war war of
the three kingdoms not that China you
okay I should not use such language here
China
three kingdoms uh Chinese civil war not
the kuin tang thing I mean why
uh Look, the three kingdoms, what does
it say? As far as I remember, 30 to 40
million people died um during this time.
Tremendous, tremendous downfall,
multiple plagues, widespread famine,
civil war obviously, which causes all
the plagues and widespread all of that.
Uh Jin, how many thousands and so on.
Okay, they're trying to hide the actual
numbers here possibly. Okay, I'll not
waste your time by trying to dig out the
figures, but the three kingdom civil
war, it had a death toll. Okay, this
happened in the 3rd century AD or
something like that. 220 to 280 AD. A
third century AD. That's right. The
death toll was about 30 to 40 million
Chinese people died. Then let's look at
the Unlan.
An unlan rebellion. Unlan. Okay, it's
able to predict my my moves. So this was
a civil war again at the midpoint of the
Tong dynasty. So it's in the So this
this happened uh in the 8th century AD
and this is again in China and if you
I'm not sure if they will tell you the
death toll but the death toll is about
30 to 40 million. 30 to 40 million okay
in the 8th century AD. Good god what on
earth is China up to? Then you have
something more recent, okay? In the mid
of the 19th century, the Taiping
rebellion.
Typing rebellion. This was a Christian
rebellion against China. Okay, typing
civil war, whatever you want to call it.
It says 20 million deaths. I think it
was about 30 million. Okay, there are
Okay, it says death toll between 20 to
30 million. And there are various
estimates. Typing rebellion. Would you
believe it? So much in China. Then you
have the Manchu conquest of China. Okay.
Manchu
conquest
conquest of China. I mean how many
people died in the Manchu conquest?
About 20 30 million here also. So this
was in the 17th century transition from
Ming to Ching or whatever they want to
call it. So this had I mean you can look
up the figures in your own time. Okay.
How many people died or whatever. The
Manchu conquest has a death toll of
between 20 to 30 million. Then you have
Then you have another thing in the 19th
century Dongan revolt.
Dongan revolt. This was a Muslim you
know rebellion against China. Hui
Muslims. So this was Yakub who was one
of the major major figures in this.
Yeah. So this had a death toll of more
than 20 million. What does it say?
Population loss of 21. Yeah. 21 million
people. combination of massacres,
migration, famine, cops, transmitted
plague and all that. Then you have the
first world war, more than 20 million
people died. Then uh then you have uh
Timur Timur Timour's conquests of of
Central Asia, Iran, India. Uh probably
more than 15 to 20 million people died
in that Timur's conquests. He was a
brutal barbarian. Then you have the
Spanish conquest of Mexico. Okay. Hernan
Cortez begins in like I said 1519. Uh at
least 10 million people must have died
just in Mexico. Uh the Aztec Triple
Alliance based out of Tenokitlan.
Then you have the Spanish conquest of
the Inca Empire in South America the
eastern western part of South America.
The Inca Empire Pakuti you know so and
so on. So the perpetrator of this was
Franchesco Pidaro and at least I would
say 78 million people died in that. And
if you look at the colonization of the
Americas, well 85 to 100 million people
were killed. Brutal. So the the and if
you look at the Turk occupation of
India, I'm pretty sure the death toll is
in the hundreds of millions. I would
even venture 500 million. And some
idiots will say, "Oh, how can it be 500
million? Our population was 300 million
at the time.
So um so this show ask show is not for
those kind of people.
All right next question.
Okay a couple of people have asked about
the French Revolution. Thamart says when
the French Revolution began in 1789 the
monarchy was overthrown. Yes the
monarchy
but why did the French Empire emerge
afterwards instead of continuing the
republic is envisioned during the
revolution? Was it because the first
republic was too weak? Or was there a
larger perhaps hidden plan to expand and
dominate the world under the guise of
republican ideals? Is this the only
cause for the French Revolution or are
there other reasons why it remains one
of the most studied and popular events
in history? And Amisha says asks a very
fundamental question. Why is the French
Revolution so famous and why is it so
deeply studied compared to various other
revolutions?
Right? The French Revolution. So if you
want to understand what caused the
French revolution, you have to go back
to 18th century Europe, the age of what
they call enlightenment, you had great
towering colossal figures like John
Loach, like Walter, like Russo, you
know, fantastic people who came up with
these concepts like individual rights.
Russo came up with the concept of the
social contract. What social contract?
He said that there has to be a a social
contract
and and this says that political power
resides among the people and governments
should be based on the consent of the
governed. So that should be the social
contract and out of this came the great
principles of liberal
liberty, equality and fraternity of all
men and later later they brought in lee
secularism. Yes. So all of these things
they created this gigantic ferment in
society in Europe particularly France.
Okay. And this gave rise to the
fantastic French revolution which was a
decade of terror
1789 to 1799 thereabouts and uh well
absolute reign of terror. Pierre was one
of the instigators and one of the major
figures. He himself was off with his
head. He himself was guillotined. Yeah.
So it was that's what happened and in
the in the kingdom the royalty Louis the
16th in Mari on 28th they were deposed
and and their heads were separated from
their bodies. They were divested of
their heads during this time. So the
French Revolution you could say was the
first Voke revolution of Europe. the old
ideals, the conservative ideals were
thrown out of the window and all these
new liberal ideas came in and and that
changed Europe forever and that changed
France forever. Even today, if you look
at France, they they kind of make fun of
the royalty. When you had the Paris
Olympics,
you had the opening ceremony in which
they making fun of Marotanet, weren't
they? They were showing her with her
head in her lap and she's singing, the
head is singing from the lap. They still
make fun of the royalty and the the
French Republic's ideals are the ideals
of the French Revolution. Even today
they've added lac.
Now
who enters the picture? Well, a
fantastic gentleman enters the picture
who was born in in Korthika. Would you
like to see where is Corika? It was not
part of France. It was part of Italy.
Okay. It was part of Italy. Let me show
you the map.
We go to Europe and uh we go to the
Mediterranean Sea and here we have K.
It's now called K. It was called
Karthika and the capital is Ayachio or
Aachu. I don't know how they pronounce
it but whatever. This was a capital and
I believe Napoleon was born there or
thereabouts. And his father fought the
French. See Italy sold this island to
France but the people of the island did
not want to be part of France. they they
identified as an Italian. So Napoleon's
father actually fought the French but
then the French prevailed and then he
became an agent of France. very smart
tactical move and he enrolled Napoleon
in in French military school schools and
all that. And Napoleon well he found the
time over there very tough because he
had a different accent and he looks
different and uh he intellectually was
very different from the ordinary French
student and so on. And then the French
revolution breaks out in 1789 and
Napoleon very smartly goes back to
Corika at the time and he sits out the
bloodiest portion of the French
Revolution. So he was born in Corika and
for some time he even uh he he even um
flirted with the idea of of of
going to the UK and becoming a an
officer in their navy. He had no actual
loyalty to France or whatever because
you know he was ruthless because he
should have been Italian. He he was made
to be French and now he was like I'll go
wherever I I can go. But anyhow he went
back to study in France and eventually
he became an officer in one of the
French armies and his the first great
thing he did was he was was his action
in the siege of Tulong. Now I could
again open the map and show you where it
happened but I've done that in the past
video. So if you are interested in the
details you can look up the siege of
Tulong or Napoleon on my channel and you
will see that video in which I've shown
the map and exactly where the entire
action happened. But the siege of Tulong
was a siege of the city of Tulong by the
Royal Navy British Royal Navy and then
the navy had blockaded the city and
Napoleon was able to end the blockade
179 first half of the 1790s.
So that made Napoleon kind of famous and
he became a big deal. And then 1795 I
think he uh there was a royalist
uprising in Paris in Pari. Okay. And
Napoleon ended the uprising by firing
cannons at protesters. He called it a
whiff of grapeshot, a whiff of
gunpowder. He fired cannons at a crowd
of protesters and ended the royalist
uprising. And that that really rose his
star.
And eventually well Napoleon engineered
a coup the coup of Dizwit Bhare 18th of
Bummer and uh he became the consul
general or whatever and uh by 1804 he
was emperor of France by 1805 he was
emperor he was king of Italy. So in
about 19 years he went from complete
obscurity to becoming the emperor of
France and king of Italy. So he
convinced the the the ring leaders you
could say of the French Revolution that
the only way to preserve the ideals of
the French Revolution was was by making
him the emperor and bringing royalty
back. What a guy. What a guy. Yes. So
that's what happened. That's essentially
the story. Now why is the French
Revolution so famous and studied so
much? Because it's been so influential
in the small region called Europe. And
the Europeans rule the world today via
the various offshoots like the US. So uh
all the even today if you look at India
you know the constitution of India I
suppose it makes some illusions to
liberty
I suppose the judiciary of India also
talks about liberty equality fraternity
and all that so it's been so influential
these are regarded as the highest ideals
in a democracy and in in liberal
democracies and all that u so you could
say it was the first you could say vocal
revolution which which overthrew the old
conservative traditions that have that
have well essentially been at the the
heart of of all human history for for
centuries if not millennia. So that's
why it's it's it's been so influential
and that's why it's studied so much.
Okay. Naan Joti Bora says could you
explain
about the gulag system during the days
of the USSR its context and the
historical significance?
Gulags were labor camps, prisons,
but not just reg regular prisons where
you you would lock up prisoners in in in
cells. These were labor camps, forced
labor.
So the there were hundreds of these
labor camps, more than 500 I'm pretty
sure, across the USSR, all the way from
the European part of the USSR all the
way to the far east of the USSR, all the
way to Sakalin.
Um
so the Kamchatka Pinsula at least okay
map map so that we understand what we're
talking about otherwise some people may
I'm sure not get the reference and the
the context and that's not your fault
it's your geography teacher's fault I
don't blame you for that so let's take a
look at the the map so the USSR
well Barus and Ukraine were part of the
USSR in those days also the Baltic
nations Latvia Lithuania and Estonia so
all the way from
all the way across Eurasian USSR all the
way up to Kamchatka. This is the U
Kamchatka Peninsula. Okay. So these
gulags were a network you could say or
an archipelago
of more than 500 forced labor camps.
Prisoners would be sent there for years,
maybe for decades and they would be made
to do forced labor. Some of these
prisoners would be just criminals and
some of them would be political
prisoners who were thrown into jail
because they were inconvenient to the
Soviet to the to the communist party of
the USSR. Uh so many dissident, many
people who wanted more rights, more
freedoms, people who wanted democracy,
people who opposed Stalin, whatever,
they were all thrown into gulags. Many
famous people went into gulags and many
of them never came out. These were labor
camps, forced labor camps and
tremendously horrific conditions,
usually very cold weather, freezing
conditions. Many people would be freed
from gulags when they were on the verge
of dying. They would be released and uh
that sort of thing. And one of the most
famous uh inmates of the gulags was
Alexander Solzitkin
uh Nobel laurate, Nobel Peace Prize uh
historian and and writer of literature.
His expose of the of the system was
called the gulag archipelago. It's a
pretty voluminous set of at least two or
three books if I I remember reading some
of it some part of it back in the day.
Uh yeah. So in in in the in this book he
describes the brutal conditions that you
have when you live in the in the gulags.
Uh one of the interesting things is uh
there is a road there's a highway in the
USSR in in Russia today. It's called the
highway of bones.
The highway of bones. So let's let me
see if I can find this highway of bones.
Shall I? Uh okay. We need to go to I
need to orient myself. I need to go to
Kamchata Magadan. So you see this road
here. You can see this road traced on
the map over here. So let's zoom in.
Zoom in and let's try and see the
satellite image of this road.
All right. Here we are. Let's zoom in
further. It's called P504, right? P504.
Let's see if we can get a street view
image of this. Do they have a street
view image? You see this road standard
looking highway? Right. So, you see this
region in the winter it freezes freezes
solid absolutely frozen over and there
are parts of this region where the
temperature in winter goes to like -50°
C.
frightening conditions, frightening uh
climatic conditions. So this highway
504,
it was constructed by slave labor, by
labor taken from the gulags and
conditions were so bad that we don't
even know how many people died there.
And because the ground was frozen, it
was permafrost.
So there was no way to bury the people.
So what they would do is they would just
put the people under the road. So this
entire road, it is alleged is paved by
the bones of prisoners who died
constructing the road. And if you don't
believe what I am saying, if it's if it
sounds too fantastic and and ridiculous,
let's Google it. Highway of Bones,
Russia, shall we? Let's Google it.
Highway of Bones
of
Bones Russia. Highway of Bones, Russia.
R4504.
Isn't that the one we just saw?
504 was it?
It was called P504 in in the map that we
just saw. So R504, Kolima Highway, M56
route, Far East, Magadan. There you have
it. It connects Magadan. It's been
colloially called the road of bones.
and um inmates of the Sevotlag labor
camp and started the first stretch and
construction continued with the use of
gulag labor until 1953.
So there you have it. It really is
called the highway of bones or road of
bones.
Um so that's how it was and and and you
know during the second world war Joseph
Stalin gave some gave a bit of amnesty
to inmates of gulags. He he gave them a
deal. Here's the deal. You fight in the
war and I'll give you either amnesty I
I'll free you from jail or maybe I'll
give you reduced terms. So once you're
done fighting if you survive then
instead of 50 years you can do just like
3 years. That sort of thing. So a lot of
people were freed from the gulags. They
fought in the war. Many of them died.
Some of them who returned survived some
of them were just freed. Some of them
were sent back to the gulags for a
shorter period of time and that gave
rise to the Suka wars. Suka wars. So
let's Google that.
What on earth? Okay, the things I show
you.
Suka wars. It's called the wars
for whatever reason. These were armed
confrontations in the Soviet gulag labor
system between 1945.
The battles took place between groups of
prisoners who agreed to collaborate with
the administration of labor camps and
prisons and honest criminals who did not
collaborate with prison authorities. So
if you have people who have been freed
and given an amnesty
and they survived the war and came back
and as long as they behaved they were to
be released in just a short amount of
time they would also obviously
collaborate with the authorities and
that was jarring for the people for for
the inmates who had not taken the
amnesty and who refused to collaborate
with the authorities. So this gave rise
to these clashes in the gulag system
between the ones who had the thief's
honor code and the ones who were called
the sukas the suki plural in Russian and
eventually the suki one s so yeah that's
what it was the gulag system was this
brutal slave labor system many political
prisoners were eaten alive by that and
lots of criminals also were part of that
and eventually I think if I'm not
mistaken by the after after stallion
died the system was gradually dismantled
and ended. So that was the gulag system.
The deal was that you know if you went
against the interests of the state of
the nation or the ch of or or the Soviet
communist party you'll be thrown into
gulags. No questions asked. That's how
it went.
Amisha Mishra says do we have any data
on how many Indians were killed during
British rule from 1757 to 1947? Well, if
you look at Indian historians and their
work, you will see nothing. Nobody has
tried to estimate this properly. If you
look at the records of the famines that
the British caused, they caused,
I would say, dozens, maybe hundreds of
famines in India, various parts of India
during the two and a half centuries that
they occupied India. And if you look at
some of these famines, famines, you had
death tolls of 5 million, 10 million.
The Madras famine of I don't know which
year caused a death toll of I think
between 5 to 10 million. and and then
you had um an auxiliary death toll which
was caused by epidemics caused by the
famine but there would not be added to
the death toll death toll of the famine.
Uh so maybe 100 plus million just from
the famines. Okay. But there were other
things. So let me I was looking at this
u some of these examples let's let's uh
go there.
So there have been various estimates
some people have estimate tried to
estimate this outside of India. So this
is u Ben Norton scholarly study found
that British colonism caused
approximately 165 million deaths in
India between 1880 to 1920 40 years 165
million people died in India the British
killed 165 million people okay in just
40 years if you don't believe this
website look here al jazer
British colonalism killed 100 million
Indians in 40 years. So at least 100
million years uh a million Indians in 40
years u just 40 years and then you have
this report from the Guardian itself.
The Guardian is a is a British newspaper
India secret history. Uh so British
reprisals reprisals involve the killing
of 10 million people over a period of 10
years after 1857.
So between 1857 to 1867 the British
killed Indians at least 10 million
Indians in in a variety of ways in uh in
revenge for 1857.
So all we have all these different
pieces of data but nobody has really
bothered to do a project and put to
compile everything together and put all
the data together and create a
systematic survey in which you can find
the real death toll. I would say if you
if you just look at these rough numbers
and you do a just a rough tally if you
take the famines it's 100 million ultra
says 100 the other one says 165 let's
say 100 so 100 plus 100 is two 200 plus
you have 1857 to 6710 that's 210 plus
all the epidemics that are not counted
the death toll of epidemics is not
counted maybe in excess of 300 million
easily that's what the British did
absolute monsters s and today they
lecture us about human rights and
freedom and all that.
And Indians are such angopiles.
They killed your ancestors. They killed
your relatives in the most brutal and
barbaric ways you can imagine.
Men, women, little children, little kids
starving to death.
Okay.
Nirvana Shanks says, "How did the Mongol
Empire grow so fast across all of
Eurasia and what were the most important
forces that made it happen? Thank you
for your attention to the to this
question." So, I did an episode on the
Mongol Empire. Maybe it was episode 2 or
three or something of the Ask Abis show.
Today's episode 278. So, maybe we can
revisit some questions about the Mongol
Empire. It's been a long time since I
spoke about the that this matter and I'm
sure a lot of subscribers have not seen
me speak about this and may may have
this questions. So we can certainly
revisit this. How did the Mongol Empire
grow so fast across all of Eurasia? What
made it happen? The most important
forces.
So
if you look at the
region of Mongolia in the 1200s, 1300s,
what was the population? Maybe a million
or two million.
Okay,
maybe a couple of million. Let's quickly
um do a quick Google search.
What is the population of Manipur today?
Okay, one second
here.
Population of Manipur.
Manipur today um 3.75
million. So Manipur is a tiny state in
the far east of India, right? 3.75
million is the population today. The
population of Mongolia was less than
that. Maybe 2 three million. Okay.
And out of that little population came
the greatest empire in human history
until that time.
So the people of Mongolia were used to
hardship.
The weather in Mongolia is essentially
the same as the weather in Lada today in
in northern India minus the altitude.
The climate in Ladak is even even
harsher than Mongolia because of the
extreme altitudes. But otherwise the
climate in Mongolia is essentially the
same as Ladak if you subtract the
effects of altitude, extreme cold and so
on and and uh lack of water etc. that
sort of thing. So the people of Mongolia
were used to extreme hardships for
centuries, for millennia
and they lived in small nomadic groups.
So they they were accustomed to a very
disciplined, very regimented lifestyle.
The moment you broke discipline, you
died. That's how bad it was. So they
were used to very tough conditions. And
they had these little clans or or
tribes, the the Borgjugin, the Olonut,
the Oruryangai
and and the the Nimmans and various
other other other tribes and all the
tribes would fight each other because of
the scarse resources. So they would try
and live as far as apart as possible but
if they came into contact they would
essentially fight and the Chinese
were the biggest instigators who kept
the tribes fighting each other. The
Chinese
so you had this people who were
accustomed to extreme hardship. They
were accustomed to living in almost a
militaristic fashion but they were
fighting each other. So somebody had to
come and unite them and that somebody
was Shri Chingghis Khan. So for the
first 43 44 maybe 45 years of his life
he spent fighting the various Mongol
clan tribes and unifying them. When he
unified them he said all right it's time
to go first let's teach the Chinese a
lesson. They have been made they've been
leading us for centuries. So that's
where it starts. So the Mongols were
already accustomed to a militaristic
lifestyle a regimented lifestyle.
Jingghis Khan weaponized that and he
enlisted the entire corpus of the
Mongolian population into the military.
Everybody
every able-bodied man or or boy became a
warrior.
Older people people became shepherds and
and tenders of livestock because their
entire food was b based on on sheep
mutton.
So that's what happened and Jish Khan
well he was a genius so he was able to
organize the Mongol army in such a way
that nobody had done before and at the
pinnacle of Chingish Khan's powers
at the pinnacle of his career the Mongol
army was at most 100,000 strong one lakh
you could fit the entire Mongol army
into the Eden Garden stadium or in
Narendra Modi stadium and with that army
he conquered half the known world.
So he conquered it through incredibly
brilliant tactics and strategies. He
also had incredibly brilliant generals
like those subotai bakad
right um the Mongols pioneered so much.
They pioneered what we now called
Britzkrieg.
They they Jungish Khan understood that
on a battlefield
it's all the flow of energy that
matters. You know he could see the
battle he could visualize the
battlefield as if he was like a
kilometer above the battlefield. He
could see how things were going. He
understood the the the role that energy
and momentum played in battles and he
innovated various battle strategies and
tactics the horn the two horns maneuver
and so much more. And the entire per
purpose of existence of of the Mongol
population was was war. That's how it
that's how it went. But Chis Khan at
least while he was alive, he only fought
just wars. He did not start war start
wars because it just felt like it. And
that's a whole different story. So
because of the this combination of
factors, it grew incredibly fast. And
they had tremendous communications.
They had a postal service. They had
communications that were like
unimaginably fast for for the 13th
century for the 14th century for the
13th century. Nobody communicated that
that at that speed. And the speed at
which the arbies moved on the
battlefield was unimaginable. And a lot
of this was thanks to the Mongolian
pony.
It's a horse that's like shorter than
the Arabian horses or whatever else.
It's very similar to the Manipuri pony
by the way. And yeah, it's the Mongolian
pony. little horse that was the battle
tank of the Mongolian armed forces. So
it was a combination of all these
factors that made this happen. Good
question. Good question. All right. Now,
next question.
Magnificent Shri Nearuji says, "How did
the Mongol Empire maintain trade and
communication across such a massive land
area?" So at its pinnacle during Shri
Chingistan's time half the known world
was conquered by the Mongol Empire
excluding India. Yeah. And uh yeah we
know the answer to the question. Um now
how did they maintain trade and
communication? Because if you want to
maintain a cohesive empire that doesn't
disintegrate spontaneously,
you need communications. You need to
know exactly what's happening in various
parts of the empire. And sometimes when
when you're talking about an empire like
the Mongol Empire, we're talking about
thousands of kilometers. So how do you
know what's happening 2,000 km away for
example, you've got to know otherwise
you lose all control.
Not only do you need to know what's
happening, you need to be able to
control what's happening. So you need
constant communication. So the Mongols
had the world's best postal service,
couer service and a system and a system
of of
u of communicators based on horses. So
they would have these check posts
at at at distances of let's say roughly
50 to 100 kilometers and you would have
fresh horses everywhere. So a guy who's
let's say going from Karakuram
to maybe
the borderlands of present day Ukraine
bearing a message from Shri Chingghist
Khan to his vas wasal there or to his
his general there. So if Shingaskhan
sends a message, he will give it to a
rider who will ride at the speed of
sound essentially as fast as possible
and the moment he reaches the next
checkpoint, he will surrender his horse
there and take a fresh horse and go and
go and go and that way they could cover
incredible distances in very short
periods of time. So that's how they were
able to maintain communication and trade
is a more leisurely thing and they they
had a proper system of trade. uh they
had free trade
so you could trade without tax and all
that as long as you were part of the
Mongol Empire. So all of this is is
thanks to the system that the that Khan
created a very very disciplined
welloganized welloiled system and that's
how was able to he was able to maintain
such a big empire but eventually the
empire became it it it outgrew him. It
outgrew the capabilities of any
communication system of that time. So
eventually
it the empire grew even further even
larger and his sons took over then went
and there to take with the various
chunks of the empire and eventually it
fragmented because of various reasons
such as infighting and so on and also
because the empire became so large that
even with the best communication system
in the world it was no longer possible
to communicate in real time or at least
in decent enough time.
Shubhanker Kulkarnney says, "I always
wonder how underrated Subai was as a
general. If it were any other European
general, large volumes would have been
written about him. Subai coordinated
large armies across thousand kilometers
and led a separate expedition where he
defeated the Armenians, Georgians, Roose
principalities, the Kummans and the
Kipchacks. I always wonder what a
brilliant military general he was. He
was Chingisan's greatest general. Jingis
Khan took him into the army
when when Subatai was about like a
teenager maybe 13 14 years old. Subotai
belonged to the Uran Kai tribe
and he quickly became um
one of the trusted lieutenants of
Chingish Khan and obviously you don't
achieve that lightly. You've got to
really prove yourself to become someone
that Chingis Khan trusts. I mean a guy
like Chingis Khan to earn his trust
you've got to be special and that to at
such a young age. So Chuatai would
always put his life life on the line and
eventually he he showed that he could
command a tuman.
A tuman was a was a division of 10,000
that was the largest regiment or
division they would have in the
Mongolian. It's essentially one separate
army and he was sent on expeditions far
and wide.
U at one point in time Chunis Khan's
eldest supposed son Joi was entrusted to
the care of of Tubotai
and they went all the way far west
Ukraine, Russia those principalities and
uh they encountered the Europeans for
the first time and defeated many of
them. Um, so that was the first set of
encounters between the the Mongols and
the Roose and and the and the Eastern
Europeans. And Subati, my god, the
coordination. I mean, he like you say,
he could coordinate different armies,
different set of sets of troops over
hundreds of kilometers and make them
move in in coordination and cohesion
and have them attack at the same time
coming from hundreds of kilometers
apart. I mean, he did that over and over
again.
How he did that, God only knows. But
that's the kind of incredible general he
was. Probably the greatest general that
we know of in history. The kind of feats
he achieved,
how how on earth did he achieve those?
And after Chingish Khan died, Subutai
served Chingish Khan's successor, his
son Ogdai, who was the second emperor of
the Mongol Empire. And under Ogdada as
as as as
Ogada as general, Subatai went and
conquered Russia, parts of Russia. So
under Chinghan, he went on
reconnaissance missions. He circled the
which sea was it? He circled One second.
Let let's see. I believe he circled the
Caspian Sea,
not the Black Sea. He circled he circled
the Caspian Sea with his with his ar
with his army on a reconnaissance
mission and then under Ogda he went and
conquered those lands. Uh underrated is
is an understatement.
One of the greatest generals possibly
the greatest general of all time.
Subotai Batir
magnificent Fhuji. What a name. What a
name sir. Okay, the question is how did
the industrial revolution improve living
standards but also call create new forms
of inequality and how can that duality
be addressed today.
Okay, let's talk about England because
the industrial revolution starts in
England, right? How does the industrial
revolution start? It starts because of
the age of Elizabeth,
I'm sorry, the Victorian age. Who was
Henry's daughter? Henry VII's daughter
8 daughter. He had two daughters. One
was Bloody Mary and the second was um
Elizabeth the first. Yes. The
Elizabethan age.
So Elizabeth
was a pretty liberal ruler. She was not
conservative like her sister Mary. Um
she was more of her father's daughter.
Henry VIII was a very well well
interesting person. And under Elizabeth
England completely transformed. She
allowed the the study of science and
physics and so on and so much happened
because of that. So the industrial
revolution has its roots in the
Elizabethan age.
Now if you look at England historically
what was the society like? We have to
understand this to understand
the effects of the industrial
revolution. Historically England society
was a continuation of the society and
and the system of society that was
imposed upon the island by the Normans
after the year 1066.
So what kind of society was it? At the
top you had the king or the queen.
Typically it was a king. Below the king,
second rank was the the nobles
who served the king. So the nobles would
generally have some holdings, land
holdings. Some would have big land
holdings, some would have smaller land
holdings and they would pay a tax to the
king every year. They were the king's
vasals and they would have
men who would work for them and then
they would have their own private
armies. And whenever the king demanded,
they would have to come and and
serve the king and have their army serve
the king.
That was the deal. And the nobles had
lands and on the lands the peasants
toiled. The peasants what did they toil?
What was the toil like? Agriculture. And
the agriculture
is what generated the revenue and the
wealth for the nobles. And a certain
percentage of that went to the church
and certain percentage went to the king
to the crown. That's how it was.
At the top you had the king. Next you
had the nobles.
Third you had the peasants and then you
had slaves.
For a time there were lots of slaves. I
mean um
during the time of William the conqueror
I suppose about 10% see about a thousand
years ago about 10% of England's
population was slaves. They would wear
copper bands around their necks and they
would die with that on that sort of
thing. So it was a pretty brutal system.
So the entire economy was based on
agriculture.
It was a feudal system.
A few a small percentage of the of the
population maybe 2 3% maybe less were
land owners. All land was technically
owned by the crown. But the nobles they
held the land were stewards of the land
for the crown in the service of of the
crown. So they would take care of of the
all the agricultural work that will
happen there. And they would give tax to
the king and some of it they would keep
and the the peasants they were
essentially owned more or less by the
nobles. They were at the mercy of the
nobles.
So that was the system. So the entire
system was based on agriculture like I
said. Now the industrial revolution
happens. The industrial revolution. So
all the wealth
historically was in the countryside
wherever you have agricultural fields
that's where the real wealth of the land
lay in England
in Britain when the industrial
revolution happened suddenly cities and
factories became the engine that
produced this new wealth
and it they were producing they started
producing way more wealth
than any wealth that could come from
agriculture. So the focus suddenly
shifted from the countryside to the
cities and the factories.
Right? So there's a lot of money to be
made there. So so so
what this did is that a new class of
people emerged. Wealthy people who were
not nobles they were the industrialists.
They were the business people and they
quickly became more wealth than the
nobles. Then the nobles some of them
pivoted and they also became
industrialists because at the end of the
day money many money matters right and
that caused a profound transformation in
the society. Lots of people started
congregating in cities moving many of
the peasants they were drawn by the
lucer by the lure of the wealth in the
cities and they also decided okay we
anyway don't own the land we are merely
working as peasants for the nobles it's
not our land we don't own it so let's go
and try our luck in the cities and we'll
go and work in a factory we'll earn more
so then the cities started growing in
size
right but in factories ri you had these
horrific abysmal living conditions.
People would work in shifts. People
would work, I don't know, 8, 12 hours a
day. I don't know what it was, but but
conditions were pretty abysmal. Child
labor was normal. Uh crime was rampant
and so on.
So this industrial revolution produced a
whole new class of elite in England in
Britain and they their wealth came from
the exploitation of people
and that was okay. I mean there was no
law against it. So they exploited
people. They exploited the peasants. So
the the peasants who did not own any
land in in in the countryside now they
were in the cities and still they did
not own any land. They were living in
rented accommodation and they were
working they were being worked to death.
So yeah it it generated a tremendous
amount of wealth. Yeah. England became
wealthier and weier and wealthier. And
there's other other you know sources of
wealth also. We will not go into that
but we're talking about the industrial
revolution. So industrial revolution is
all about machines. It's about mass
production. It's about assembly lines
and all that. So if you do that wealth
is generated fast but the wealth was
concentrated among the elites and that
eventually gives rise to what you know
the complaints of Shri Khal Mars.
Um
so yeah it it kind of lays raised living
standards. cities became wealthy and u
you had uh eventually you had the
technology that that made things better.
You had street lights and proper roads
and
things like that but it also caused
tremendous inequality because of the
entire nature of society. The society
remained an an a deeply inequal unequal
society. it became feudalism of a new
kind an industrial kind of feudalism
right and that
has continued
I mean uh the same continued
in in the Americas for example
in the Americas also you have these
industrialists and these wealthy uh
tycoons or whatever oil tycoons oil
barons the Rockefellers etc they also
continue the same thing assembly line
workers and so on uh but for some time
in America it was better. So you see the
the thing is that no society has
complete equality. It's impossible to
achieve complete equality. All you can
do is give everybody the equal rights
equal rights and and the same similar
starting point for everybody. Uh but uh
that that works in theory not in
practice. How can that be addressed
today? You can't ever address inequality
completely. What you can do is give
everybody equal rights and give
everybody equal opportunities and then
see how they go. That's what you can do.
Obviously, some people be will be born
into wealthy families. You can't do a
thing about that. Obviously, you can't
take away their wealth. You should not.
Their families are wealthy. Hopefully,
because they earned the wealth and so
on. So, essentially, that's what
happened during the industrial
revolution. That's what transformed
British society from an
agriculture-based feudal society to an
industry-based feudal society. and it
continued the inequality which you
already had in in British soc in English
society that never went away.
Uh so yeah that is what happened during
the uh industrial revolution.
Davan
Krishna says uh could you please explain
how countries in Southeast Asia became
part of the Indosphere and how Singapore
became democrat dem demographically
Chinese. Why are there efforts to
destroy evidence of an ancient Hindu
roots in countries like Malaysia? Okay,
multiple questions. We'll focus on the
main thing
essentially two questions. How did
countries in Southeast Asia become part
of the Indosphere? That process began
more than 3,000 years ago. It began with
trade trade activities. You see the east
coast of India, we have forgotten about
it completely. Let's go to the map.
We have completely forgotten the east
coast of India and what it has
contributed to our culture, civilization
and history. So let's look at the east
coast of India.
I am talking about Kolinga now called
Odisha.
The the northern part of Odisha is
called Utkal, right? What is Utkal? It's
Uttar Kalinga.
Kolinga has this incredibly ancient,
incredibly rich history as part of India
is is a is a subset of Indian
civilization. So merchants from Kolinga
were trading with Southeast Asia which
was called Subarabumi at the time. I at
least 2,000 years ago it was called
Sabumi. So merchants from Kolinga were
crossing the ocean on ships and going
all the way to Cambodia, Laos, Vietnam,
Cambodia and Vietnam also obviously uh
Thailand, Indonesia etc. They were
trading with these regions at least
3,000 years ago if not more than that.
And slowly
this caused the Indianization and
Hinduization of the entirety of
Southeast Asia. About 2,000 years ago,
Indonesia became Hindu. I mean, it was
it was Hindu. All of this entire region,
present day Indonesia, Cambodia,
Thailand, Myanmar, Vietnam, Laos,
um Myanmar, I said Philippines, all of
this was Hindu.
And much of this region has been Hindu
for more than 2,000 years, maybe around
3,000 years. all because of the uh
merchants from Kolinga who would go and
trade with these these countries and
these countries slowly adopted Indian
customs and uh they they formed great
kingdoms and empires in their own own
own right so that is what happened
that's how this region became part of
the indosphere we never ever imposed
anything on on the people of this region
there was never any religious conversion
there was never any conquest except had
the Chola conquest which was a
geopolitical affair not anything else.
So that is the deal. Now what about
Singapore? So Singhapur Singapore is
over here at the tip southern tip of the
Malay Peninsula. What happened to
Singapore? Obviously it's called Sing
Singhapur, right? The city of of of
lions. It's a Sanskrit name. So
obviously it was Hindu in the past. So
what happened? Why is it demographically
Chinese? I mean today Singapore has a
Chinese majority. What happened is the
question. How did that happen?
A city that's part of the that's at the
southern tip of the Malay Peninsula. How
how is it major majority Chinese? You
see this region came under the
came under British occupation
about a couple of around the 19th
century. Okay. So in the first quarter
of the 19th century the British
established
um colony in Singapore let's say and the
imported Chinese labor
they imported Chinese labor there and we
discussed some of the biggest wars that
have happened earlier in this episode uh
the Taiping re rebellion and the the
Dungan revolt and all that. So all of
that caused a tremendous amount of
instability in chi in China in the
middle of the 19th century. So that
caused a bigger exodus of Chinese out of
out of China elsewhere. Many of them
came to Singapore and the British
imported Chinese specifically. So over
time China's the Chinese population of
Singapore grew from like negligible
levels to 10% then eventually slowly
over by the end of the 19th century it
became the Chinese became the majority
population in Singapore. Uh so that's
how chi Singapore became gradually
demographically Chinese majority. That
is how it happened. Um well about
Malaysia well it's an Islamic country.
So well that's how it goes.
Yajjulka says
where old they were worshiing Iranian
religions in Vic Hinduism in Gandhar
persecuted under Zoroastrinism
for example under zeris in Gandhar were
the das treated as false gods and demons
by the prophets zaratustra was the
spread of Zoroshidanism in Persia
peaceful
or did it involve intolerant proactive
conversion
So
Persia, when we talking about Persia of
of ancient Persia, we're talking about
the Aminid dynasty. The first king of
the Aminid dynasty was Akeis according
to the according to the Greeks.
His name so there's this two word
there's confusion about his name, right?
What was his real name? Was it Akinus?
That's not a Persian name.
His name was either Hakamanish or
Hakamanish possibly Hakamanish.
Hakamanish.
What does Haka mean? See in Persian Sa
becomes ha.
The Indian sa becomes her in Persian.
So if you want to say
saraspati, you say harawati. So, so the
word for one of the words for friend
in Sanskrit is saka. Saka, right? So,
the Persian equivalent would be Hakka.
So it's possibly Hakamanish
who was the founder of the Akimerid
dynasty
and he is said to have lived
before Zaratustra
or Zoroaster
which means that Hakamanish would have
been Hindu
right so he would have practiced the old
religion
and then eventually at some point in
time there's the rise of the religion of
zeratustra
and somehow it spreads all over Persia
and Persia becomes becomes Zoroastrian.
Now the problem is that we don't have
any records from those times.
Persia obviously was a highly evolved
civilization,
wasn't it? It was a great civilization.
It was burned to the ground by Alexander
and the Greeks.
It was burned. The great city of
Parshapur was destroyed. Burned in a
drunken night by Alexander. They blame
some woman companion of his whatever.
And whatever records the Persians had
were destroyed. So we don't know how the
mechanics and dynamics of how
Zoroastrinism became the dominant force,
the dominant religion in Persia.
We don't know what happened and we don't
know if there was any persecution, any
forcible conversion. We don't know how
it happened. It's entirely unknown. It's
lost in the mists of time. The Greeks
destroyed the records. The Greeks,
their justification was that, you know,
the Persians had a couple a century and
a half ago burned Athens. So, they did
this in retaliation. Look, that's okay.
Whatever. That's history. But they they
burned they destroyed Persia. They took
all the gold all the gold of Persia
away. They begged Persia.
And yeah, that's what happened. So, we
don't know what happened.
We don't know if it was brutal, if if it
was peaceful or it it involved
intolerant
forceful conversion. We have no idea.
But we know what we know is that the
Zoroshan religion, the religion of
Zaratustra is kind of an inversion of
the Vic religion.
It has the same elements but kind of
inverts things. So the das become bad
guys and the assuras become the good
guys. In Vic religion, you know, the
dwas are the good guys and the assuras
are are kind of naughty, a little bit
naughty. They the assuras are also
divine beings, but they are kind of
naughty divine beings. Slightly slightly
naughty, not entirely evil, but not
entirely the good guys, but but the das
are the good guys. So in Zoroastrianism,
the das become the bad guys and the
assuras become the good guys. So it's
kind of a revolt of some kind. Not that
I will disown my religion but I will
invert my religion that sort of thing.
So that's what zaratust did and he came
up with this new concept of aurora mazda
the supreme brahman or what there that
that sort of thing a supreme divinity
but it's not monotheistic zostism is not
a monotheistic religion I don't care
what the westerners say to hell with the
westerners it's our culture I mean kind
of our culture we have parcels in India
ask them
ask them whether zorism zorism is a is a
monotheistic religion it's not a
monotheistic religion I don't care what
the westerners say. I don't need their
lectures. We don't need them teaching us
our our history. I consider Iran and
person history to be kind of part of our
our overall history, you know, broader
our history, our our region. Uh so we
don't know what happened. We don't know
if there was persecution or not. But
what we know is that there was never any
conflict between India and Persia. Never
ever. And when the Arabs
destroyed Persia, the Persians wish that
India would come to their help. So when
you are when you are in your worst
times, who do you wish would come to
your help? Your your people, right? Your
relatives.
Yeah. But did it not happen because at
that time India was not unified under a
single empire. So my point is that I'm
not sure eventually the das the das were
looked upon as kind of demons eventually
over time in Zoroastrianism.
uh but there was never any conflict with
India ever. So yeah that is what
happened. We have lost the records the
po records of Persian history written by
the Persians themselves because the
Greeks destroyed it. Alexander destroyed
it.
Um
Yulka says in the battles between
Greekeaking regions of Southeast Europe
and the Aminate Empire that happened a
bit pre Alexander the Greek. Do we have
any reports from Persians from the
Persian side? Are there reports of these
battles available today by later Greek
and are the reports of these battles
available today by later Greek and Roman
authors believable? Well, once again you
have hit the heart of the issue, right?
Um
you've had battles between Greek
speaking religions regions of Southeast
Europe and the Aminant Empire. The
Akminate Empire was a pretty
expansionist empire. the empire
of the descendants of Hakam.
Um, Daros, Xerxes, Xerxes, his real name
was Kay.
It was not Xerxes. Okay. And Dios was
Davos.
Cyrus was Kurush.
Uh, Kambesus was Kambujia. All the names
are names we can recognize. These are
not Greek names. The Greeks have given
their own names. So the Amirid Empire,
the Persian Empire was always
expansionist. They always expanded
westwards.
Their their enemies were the Greeks.
They wanted to conquer Greece. And Chay
tried that, right? He kind of succeeded
actually
the you know 300 that story. It was
actually 700. uh
this great expansionist empire never
ever ever even considered expanding
eastwards towards India. Never, always
westwards. Greeks, we'll fight the
Greeks. Never the Indians. There must be
some reason for it. Now, you had all
these battles and wars that happened.
And we only have reports that are Greek
reports. We don't have any Persian rec
records, right? We don't have any
reports written by Persians. It's always
reports written by Greeks and Romans.
Why is it? Because the Persians
eventually conquered uh the Greeks
eventually conquered Persia. Alexander
did. Alexander destroyed Persia,
wiped it clean, burned it to the ground.
That's what he did. Everything was
destroyed. No records available.
Everything is gone. Only the
Bhagastthana in inscription is left.
Behistun inscription it's called today.
Behistun was once called Bhagastthana
and it's written in the Persian
language. If you read it, it sounds like
Sanskrit.
uh so we don't have reports from the
Persian side and the reports of battles
available by Greek and Roman authors
will obviously you have to take them
with a grain of salt because they will
embellish
their glory and all that they will
embellish the reports and make it pro
make it sound like the Greeks were
better superior and the Persians were
naughty and bad and evil and inferior
obviously you do that right history is
written by the victor so yeah you can't
really believe those records entirely
Alexandria Yeah, Navala says, "Was Alex
al Alexandria Egypt founded by Alexander
the Greek or is this also a hoax?"
It well, as far as I know, it was
founded by Alexander. See, Alexander is
said to have founded multiple cities
called Alexandria all over the place.
Multiple Alexandrias including a couple
of Alexandria in Western India.
Allegedly, we have never found any
evidence of any Alexandria in Western
India. Never. Archaeologists have
searched for it for decades or for for
centuries, centuries. We have never
found any Alexandria in western India,
northern India, northern western India,
Gandhar, wherever. We have never found
it. He is also said to have founded
Alexandria and Skia, Alexandria and
other parts of the of possibly Persia,
Mesopotamia. We have found no
Alexandrias. But there's one aliscandria
in Egypt. It's called Aliskandria.
or would you like to look at it? Let's
take a look at it. We shall look at
Alexandria in Egypt. And that is most
likely a city that was actually founded
by Alexander the Greek. So this is one
Alexandria that actually exists and it
was founded by the guy.
Um and it still exists and u there used
to be I believe a great lighthouse there
and a great library there and it is said
that Alexander is buried in Alexandria.
It is said that one of the tombs of some
Islamic saint there is actually u
Alexander in disguise. I mean it it used
to be Alexander's tomb allegedly and
after the Islamic uh the takeover of the
region by by Islamic forces they
converted that into allegedly an Islamic
saints tomb so that it will not be
destroyed by the the the conquerors by
the occupiers. That's that's what one
hears but I don't know which tomb it is
and anyway I don't I have no intention
of visiting. So
uh Nirvana Shanks says do you think the
world would be a very different place if
the library of Alexandria had never been
destroyed? Thank you for your attention
to this question. So Alexandria is said
to have had a great library. Great
library. And we just took a look at
Alexandria the map. So what happened to
that library?
Yes. What happened? It was burned. Who
burned it?
Julio. Julius. Julius Caesar. Well, his
his army. His army burned it. And it is
said that, you know, they were they they
had to set fire to some ships to to to
prevent a rebellion from spreading or
something. And the fire spread across
the city and it burned the library. Not
our fault. We didn't mean to do that.
That sort of thing. But truth is, Julius
says it burned the library at
Alexandria. And it is have said to have
had tens of thousands of scrolls and
whatnot and all all that all that
knowledge disappeared from the world
sadly. Well, yeah, it's it's sad. It's
the burning of any library is
unfortunate, especially an Egyptian
library. And you know, imagine the kind
of knowledge that would have been there.
we would have had a much uh much richer
understanding of Egyptian history and
much more of the world's history of that
region if that library had survived
until today. Yeah.
So would the world have been a different
place? Kind of to some extent. But I'll
tell you what have would have made the
world a really different place
if the libraries
in Indian universities had not been
destroyed. That would have made the
world a genuinely different place.
Nalanda, Takshashila, Tilhara, Vikrram
Shila, Odontapuri,
Walabi, Shahit.
Each of these universities had massive
magnificent libraries. Each were
destroyed. Each each of these libraries
was destroyed.
If those libraries had not been
destroyed, that would have made the
world a completely different place.
So that I hope puts things in the right
perspective and gives the right context.
Yajjulka says and we're talking about
okay did the religion founded by
have an influence on Judaism? So Aken
what does the the name Aken mean?
Well, as a kid,
when I was about what I don't know, 11
12 years old, I read
the history of civilization by Will
Durand. It's a set of 12 books, big
thick books and I read the Egyptian part
of the history and that had a section
obviously on Akiratan. So Akaratan was
married to the queen Nefertiti that very
famous lady u whose statue still who
whose face portrayed the statue still
survives and she's regarded as one of
the you know most iconic ladies in in
world history. So she was the wife of
Akinatan Akenatan. Now Akenatan the name
it means aten is happy or at is pleased.
Who is at? So Akiratan had started this
new religion, a monotheistic religion,
son worship. There's only one god in the
world and we we said the son is the god
and akinatan means at pleased or at is
happy. My monotheistic god is pleased.
So he tried to impose monotheism on
Egypt.
He tried to undo centuries of Egyptian
tradition and culture by imposing
monotheism in Egypt. And once he died,
his son undid that and brought back
Egyptian polytheism. And Akenithan's
images and statues are all defaced and
disfigured today. So that was a damn
memory or something what what they call
you know damnation of memory. The
erasure of this person from from history
attempts to erase him from history. So
he introduced a monotheistic religion
which he invented and forced it down the
throats of the Egyptian people. Did not
work. But while he was alive, it was the
official state religion. Um, now Akathan
is said to have lived around sometime in
the 14th century BC. Shall we look it up
quickly? Let's look it up quickly. When
did he live?
Let's go to Google
and let's see. Akatan.
So let's quickly go to Wikipedia. Always
remember Wikipedia is not necessarily a
source of correct correct information
but let's just look at this for for you
know for saving time. Uh 1353 to 1336 or
1351 to 1334 BC. So the 14th century BC
right that's that's when this guy ruled
and let's ask this question when were
the Israelites
in Wow they found it. it's able to
predict predict what I'm going to ask
the exodus. So some scholars place the
enslavement around 1700 BC some say
around 13th century BC. So it looks like
it is somewhere around that time period.
They don't really we don't even know if
this enslavement actually even happened
but it is said to have happened
according to the book of the exodus and
whatnot. So if the Israelites were
enslaved in Egypt at the time when
Akaraten was in power then they would
have been exposed to monotheism.
the the religion of the Israelites
originally was polytheistic but then
Moses introduced
No, it was Abraham who introduced
monotheism. Right. Right. So if the
Israelites were actually indeed
enslaved for some time in Egypt and if
they were exposed to Akenatan's
monotheism then it's possible that
perhaps it may kind of have influenced
their belief system theology and maybe
it would have had an influence on
Judaism which eventually became a
monotheistic religion. It's possible,
but we don't have conclusive evidence of
that. But it's an intriguing
possibility.
But we don't even know for sure if this
enslavement, this incarceration of the
Israelites actually happened in Egypt.
Because thus far, we have found
absolutely not a single shred of
evidence of the existence of Jewish
people, Israelite people in Egypt during
the Pharohic ages.
Okay. Next,
Amisha says, "How powerful was the Roman
Empire?" Well, it was pretty powerful.
It was a pretty large empire. Uh, it
controlled the entirety of the Med
Mediterranean rim from the southern part
of Europe, the Mediterranean portion of
Let's go to the map.
Okay, so let's put the map on the
screen.
And if you look at the Mediterranean
region,
so all of Italy was obviously conquered
was part of Rome, but the Romans
eventually
uh conquered Hispania, Iberia, Spain,
France, which was Gaul at the time, uh
the Balkan region, obviously Greece,
obviously Julius personally conquered
Greece. Uh Anatolia obviously was used
to be a part of Greece. uh Judea which
is present day the Israel region. Syria
was a was a Roman u colony, Jordan, all
of that, Egypt was part of Rome, part of
Rome. Libya, yes, of course. Northern
Africa, all of this was part of Rome.
Yes, it was all part of the Roman
Empire. If you look at Europe itself,
proper Europe proper. Uh all of France,
it was then called Gaul. Sis Alpine,
France alpine, gold, all of that that
was part of the Roman Empire. Germania,
Germania was part of part of Rome. Um,
Skitia, part of Skitia, Trace was part
of of the Roman Empire. Um, all of this,
much of Europe was part of Rome. Even
the British islands, North Ireland, the
Romans never venture to Ireland, but all
the way to Northern England, not
Scotland, but yeah, so all of that and
they had was all over the place. And the
Romans at various points in time fought
the Persians and the Roman Empire was
actually once captured by the Persians
and humiliated rather badly. So
eventually the Romans were fighting our
neighbors the Persians. Right? So
obviously it's clear from this from just
looking at the map that it is it used to
be a pretty powerful empire pretty
powerful and it was in power for a very
long period of time multiple centuries.
And once the western Roman Empire which
was based out of Rome, it declined and
fell and became part of the it was
totally totally destroyed by by the Holy
Roman Empire eventually. But the Eastern
Roman Empire based out of Bzantion or
Constantinople. It remained a powerful
empire until the Turks took over 15
whatever. Right? So the Eastern Roman
Empire was was in power for much longer
even after Rome fell. Right. So
Constantinople fell in 1453
to to that guy whatever his name was the
Turkish guy. So pretty powerful pretty
powerful no question about that.
Nirvana Shanks says which Indian
maritime trade route had the biggest
cultural impact beyond the subcontinent?
Thank you for your attention to this
question. So India had multiple trade
routes. Let's once again go to map. Once
again we go to map and we'll try and
trace out some of these trade routes
that we had. India was from the rig vic
days a maritime civilization.
So during well what we call the Sarasati
synindu phase of our history we were
trading with Mesopotamia. We know that
because our you know seals from the
Sarasati Hindu Sindu region are found
all across Mesopotamia.
Um we had uh trading centers in in the
Gulf region. We were trading with uh
Ilam Ilam and Marashi and Mesopotamia.
So we had trade routes there. Then we
were trading with Africa. We were
trading with Egypt because we have found
artifacts of our our existence there. We
were trading with Rome and the Romans
used to complain that we were that that
India was taking all of Rome's gold in
exchange for spices. uh then we were
trading with Sarna Bhumi and uh yeah
that's about it u we are talking about
maritime routes over here so these are
the major trade routes we had now which
had the biggest impact beyond the
subcontinent
I would say the eastern trade route to
suburbi it had most likely the biggest
impact because it completely Indianized
this entire vast region it's a huge
region ra it is larger than Jammu. If
you look at the entire uh geographical
extent of the region, if you look at all
the Indonesian islands, if you look at
the Philippines, if you look at Subaru
Nabumi, Southeast Asia, which is
Thailand, Vietnam, Cambodia, Myanmar,
Vietnam, all of that huge huge area. All
of that was completely Indianized,
completely Hinduized, right? Through
trade, only through trade, not through
force or violence at all.
So clearly this was the biggest cultural
impact we had. We also had you know an
impact huge huge impact in Africa but
that has now diminished because of the
passage of time and the decline of
Indian civilization.
All right.
Shubhanker Kulkarnney says why in why
did Indians eventually give up ship
building and traveling the oceans by the
16th or 17th century? We have records of
cholas going as far east as Vietnam and
Cambodia while Indian traders were
present even in Africa and played a key
role in well our trade with Rome. Yes.
Is the Turkish occupation of India which
started this inward is it the Turkish
occupation of India that started this
inward-looking mentality. Indians at one
at one point in time had really good
ships and were excellent navigators. You
see when Vasco the Gama crossed went
around the Cape of Good Hope and arrived
in Eastern Africa
he thought at that time that he had the
world's most powerful ships the most
advanced ships in the world and when he
reaches east Africa I think Mombasa or
somewhere Kenya Tanzania that region he
sees ships that are three times the size
of his ship these are Indian ships you
have Indian merchants there but these
are peaceful ships without any weapons
so he takes he he takes the help of an
Indian merchant Apparently we don't know
who he was but that's how he he
discovered India. That's how he he was
able to reach India and that's where all
the colonization nonsense starts. So
India had tremendous ship building
seafaring capabilities and they were
used for this was used for trade trade
and we had a huge presence in Africa
eastern Africa and also in Sabumi all of
that. Now what happened?
What happened is that we came under
foreign occupation. First by the Turks
and then by the Europeans
while the Turks were ruling India, they
were not in control of all of India.
They were control of in control of parts
of India and parts of India were still
free and those parts of India were still
trading with other other parts of the
world because we were a trading nation,
a maritime nation and uh our kings, our
kingdoms, our empires encouraged trade.
So it was part of our DNA.
So we were doing this and we had
tremendous ship building capabilities.
Now as the Turk occupation spread like a
cancer. The Turk rulers had no interest
in trade with other countries and
facilitating Indian trade with other
other countries. They were extractors.
They had other items on the agenda.
So they discouraged trade. they I mean
they conducted genocide obviously and
they had no real interest in in you know
patronizing trade and and helping that
out. So that caused a slow decline in in
our trading uh activities. When the
Europeans came to power and they took
over parts of India eventually the whole
of India they destroyed
our trade. They de-industrialized India
systematically
but they did keep some ship building
alive in India for their own purpose for
their own benefit. Lots of European
ships were then built in India. Some of
the ships that were that that took part
in the in the American war of
independence in the in the yeah American
war of independence most likely
they were made in India. some of the
ships that
that participate in the US civil war
possibly were were made in India
and so on. Yeah. So
so that that's what that was the thing.
So because the Europeans the British
systematically and purposefully
deliberately deemed us as India that's
how all of this eventually disappeared.
And today in in India people don't even
know that we used to be a maritime
civilization. The leading maritime
civilization
with the most advanced ship building
capabilities.
Yeah. And today look at us. So
right
okay let's see some a couple more
questions. Jajnavulka says the book
Exotic Aliens the lion and the cheetah
in India written by Rmula Tapar aal
seems to have tried to show that the
lion was not native to India and was
imported to India around the time of
Alexander's invasions.
Now Mmanuel Eal the evolutionary history
of extinct and living lions 2020 seems
to have concluded that the lion existed
in India from a very long time much
before the time of Alexander. So how
could a supposed historian like Robinata
write an entire book to propagate a big
lie? I'll tell you what, there are Indas
Valley Harapan Sarasati Hindu era seals
and pottery that depict lions.
Alexander was not born for for a few
thousand years after that.
We had lions for we've always had lions.
But why does somebody like Rome try to
prove that there were no lions in India?
And Alexander the Greek he he he blessed
us with lions. All good things come from
outside from the west. Right? See Romeir
Tappar is a very problematic uh esteemed
person.
There is she has tried to distort a lot
of things in the past. There is a Vic
text. It's called the Bodhana
Shro Sutra. Let's Google. Let's Google
it quickly to see some of her her other
achievements. Okay, let's go to
Wikipedia and let's see if that what it
says. Okay, bodana
shro
let's go to Wikipedia and see what see
what this has to say. It's a late Vic
text dealing with the Solomon etc etc um
etc blah blah blah blah blah blah blah
poor legend translation controversy so
according to Michael Vidzel some Vic
passages point to the Indoarian
migration huh and Michael Vidzel
translated this passage of the bodhan
sutra
to interpret it as evidence in favor of
arian migration
um Amasu went eastu
went eastwards
and his people the kurup panchchal and
the kashi vid eta this is the arian
migration and so on and rmula taper
stated this passage contained literary
evidence of an arian no invasion now
they have changed it to migration it
used to be invasion if you look at the
history of this article it'll show
invasion
so ruler used Michael Witell's
translation
to say that there was an arin invasion
but this is an incorrect translation
this was deliberately flawed
translation. If you actually if you
actually know Sanskrit, you will see
that this text speaks of a westward
migration towards central Asia of
Indians.
Okay.
So,
so it's clear that these people have in
the past on multiple occasions tried to
distort Indian history. The Bodhyana
Shrot Sutra talks about a Vic king late
Vic king called Abavasu who migrates
westwards.
His people are the Gandhara the Parha
and the Arata. Gandhara obviously
Afghanistan Para means Persia. Arata
could be Armenia. So that could show our
connection with these regions. Persia
and Afghanistan we anyway know our
connection but possibly Armenia.
So Michael Vidzel did a incorrect
translation and Rome took that and tried
to propagate the Arin invasion theory.
It's been completely debunked today.
Nobody believes that Michael Witzell
translation. Anyone who knows Sanskrit
will tell you that it's a westward
migration, not an eastward migration. So
Robin has in the past done these things.
She has a track record of of doing this.
So what can I say? It's no surprise that
she has tried to claim that the lion was
brought into India by by a westerner.
because we had no good things in India.
Yeah.
Um,
okay. I have a lot more questions but
I'm going to end it here. So, let's take
some questions from the comments. If you
have some life live questions you would
like to ask me about history about
history about history, ask me. And uh, I
will not take other questions. I'll only
take Yes. Yes, you're right sir. Arian
picnic theory. Arian picnic theory. It
used to be the Arian invasion theory.
They were able to find no evidence of
invasion. So they said no it was not
invasion it was migration. Migration
they came peacefully and migrated. So
then where's the evidence of the
migration? Then they said no it was
multiple small waves of migration.
Multiple small waves of migration. So
that also has not worked. Where are the
multiple small waves of migration? Show
me the archaeological evidence. Show me
one shred of evidence of small waves of
migration. That's not there. So they'll
say it was not migration. It was
tourism. They came as tourists. Even
that one work. So they will now say
picnic. So Arian invasion theory will
become has become arian migration
theory. Then migration theory will
become tourism theory and then it
eventually it will become a picnic
theory and then they will say alien
invasion theory. None of these are going
to is going to work. There was no Arian
invasion migration whatsoever. We are
the Arya people. If there were Arian
invasions or migrations they were out of
India and that's the end of the story.
I don't care what godamn genetic
evidence you put in front of me. The
crux of the matter is Hinduism and and
Sanskrit, not genetics. A huge place
like India, obviously we had migr
migrants coming all the time. It proves
nothing whatsoever.
Okay. Questions about history, please,
not about civic sense and god knows
what.
Um,
okay. Shri Ramchandra says, "Why did
World War II happen quickly after World
War I?" Well, it's the same conflict. I
call it the European tribal wars.
It's the same conflict. The end of the
sec of the first world war was
humiliation
for Germany. The treaty of Vai was
for Germany. And that
caused that that that
co that created the conditions for the
rise of a German black backlash because
Germany was humiliated.
Germany was Germany's pride was
destroyed. Eventually somebody would try
and reclaim that pride, right? So
Germany was made to pay pay huge
reparations. Germany was made to give up
territory. all kinds of humiliations,
right? All kinds of humiliating
conditions in Germany. So then you have
in 1935 the rise of a painter who says I
will restore German pride
and then unfinished business has to be
taken care of. So that that is the
reason you see it all starts with uh the
crisis of 1914 and Austro-Hungarian
Empire which was dismantled entirely and
then it it all ends with well Hiroshima
and Nagasaki.
Okay.
Geopolitical says how advanced were
Indian methodological techniques
compared to civilizations like Egypt or
Mesopotamia.
Well, you see we have certain pillars in
India. You go to Delhi, there's a pillar
standing there, right? Those pillars
have been standing for centuries in the
weather.
Iron pillars, not steel, iron pillars.
They've been standing in the in the
weather in the Indian monsoon, the sun,
the heat, the rain, the snow, whatever
is there.
No deterioration whatsoever.
Till today, engineers and scientists
can't tell you how that sort of that
that iron was created, how the was that
iron smelted, what was the technique
behind it. Nope. We don't know.
The world's greatest and best steel, the
best steel of all, best steel of all was
crucible steel.
It was being smelted in India in
southern India. Even in Sri Lanka,
present day Sri Lanka around 500 BC.
When Alexander the Greek came to India,
he discovered this. It was like the
greatest thing he had ever seen. Sir, it
has been given various names. Crucible
steel, cerak steel. Now it is called
Damascus steel.
It's Indian steel. So our methological
techniques were were beyond anything the
west or any other part of the world
could achieve. Tremendous. Tremendous.
Okay.
Um
Dark Edit says, "Okay, this is the last
question for today. Last question.
Whether Kushans, Indians or Central
Asians everywhere, they say they're
Central Asian invaders. Of course they
will say that. Of course they will say
they are foreigners. The foreigners
see the Kushans
they came from which part of the world?
They invaded India. Yes, agree. No
questions.
No question. They came from which part
of the world? They uh let's go to the
map.
Let's put the map on the screen.
So the Kushans they came from the Tarim
basin region present day Singinjang
currently occupied by by China. What is
this river? This is the Kotan river.
There's a Tarim river somewhere here.
Um
what is this Tarim River? Where is Tarim
River? It's somewhere in this region.
Okay. So the Tarim basin region is
somewhere around here. uh, Hotan and all
that. The Kushans came from this region.
They came.
So if you look at this region, this was
the region
that was home to the Tushara people of
the Mahabharat.
In English, they call them the
Tokarians. The Tokarians.
And if you look at the Tarim region
today, you will find mummies there.
People who who were buried around 2,000
30,000 BC. The tarim basin mummies
these were the tokaran people they spoke
the tokaran language and if you look at
the tokaran script it goes k ga all that
so it was an indic kind of language it
was based on an indic system if you look
at the DNA of the tarim based in mummy's
male DNA it is R1 A1A it is classic
Indian DNA even though these people have
blue eyes possibly and possibly red hair
and white skin so they were the Tushara
people leche people but related to
Indians.
You could say that they were the eastern
mostians, the Koshans,
not really Central Asians.
So, and the Skians
were people who in a very distant time
in history
migrated out of India possibly as as a
consequence of a defeat in a battle in a
war maybe the battle of the 10 kings. So
the skitians and the Kushans are related
were always related to us there. If you
look at the Tarim basin cities which are
still found in the in the in ruins in
ruin form in the deserts you will see
frescos and paintings of Lord Ganesh
Lord Shiva
all that. So they were culturally Indian
linguistically possibly different
ethnically they had similar DNA. Armen
is the classic Indian uh genetic hlo
group, male petrole hyper group. So they
were related to Indians. They must have
been outside of India for several
thousand years but they were related to
us. And when they invaded India and
conquered parts of India, they were able
to assimilate harmoniously
like sugar in milk. There were no ethnic
clashes, no religious tensions, nothing.
Same for the Skithians. So yes, they
came from Central Asia, but they were
culturally, ethnically, civilizationally
very similar to us. And the Kushan
Empire did more than I cannot think of
anybody else. Did more than anyone I can
think of
to further propagate Indian culture and
civilization far beyond India's
boundaries.
I mean, what how much more Indian do you
want somebody to be? Yeah. Okay. They
came from outside. I don't care. I don't
care. They came from what? What part of
the world? They were civilizationally
like far more Indian than many Indians
today. Understand that. So that's what I
would say and so on.
Okay, I'm going to end this today. So
thank you so much. We've gone way past
two 2 hours. So better end it now. Thank
you so much for all the questions. I had
more questions that I had selected but I
ran out of time. When I when I do a
history live stream, it's always like
this. So many very interesting
questions. So, how about we do one
history live stream a week and we can we
can make the other one a geopolitics
live stream. I can make it a super chat
live stream. That sort of thing. I think
it'll be very interesting. Yeah. So, all
right. Thank you so much for the
questions. I will see you in tomorrow's
geopolitics liveream. Keep learning,
keep asking questions, and don't forget
to keep raising your standards. Thank
you so much. Take care. I'll see you
tomorrow. Good night. Good day. Bye-bye.